<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>drlikith blog</title>
    <subtitle>my blog</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://drlikith.com/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drlikith.com"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://drlikith.com/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>about</title>
        <published>2025-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-09-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              likith
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drlikith.com/about/"/>
        <id>https://drlikith.com/about/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://drlikith.com/about/">&lt;p&gt;why is it so hard to write about myself&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>on home</title>
        <published>2025-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              likith
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drlikith.com/blog/on-home/"/>
        <id>https://drlikith.com/blog/on-home/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://drlikith.com/blog/on-home/">&lt;p&gt;I have moved cities&#x2F;countries at least six times now, with the total number of times I have moved easily reaching double digits. Suffice it to say I have learnt a thing or two about the concept of “home”.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-home-means-to-me&quot;&gt;what home means to me&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definition of home that I learnt a long time ago, that it is a particular place, that you might long for while you are away from it, didn’t quite resonate with me. The view that home is a feeling, however, did make sense to me on multiple levels.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, is a person who grew up in a very abusive, hell-hole of an environment doomed to be forever alien to the concept?
Of course not, but this perspective didn’t come easily to me. With each and every house that I lived in, with each new city that I grew even somewhat comfortable with navigating, I learnt more about myself as much as I did about the place itself and a few people around me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-few-things-i-ve-learnt&quot;&gt;a few things I’ve learnt&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that feeling at home in a place requires, in somewhat equal parts, getting to know and being more comfortable with both what is around you, as well as what is within you.
Building a life in a place that is new to you demands that you understand your values, your likes, tastes, passions, and of course, the things that make you uncomfortable.
I have also found that when you are even somewhat in touch with your internal value system, you make it easier for yourself to be able to make a given place feel like home.
My experiences have also taught me that the people you grow up depending on seldom stay necessary. Take this with a grain of salt, but we often grow up idolising and learning that these people are essential to our growth, comfort, etc., but it so happens that they are just a couple of other people. And just like any other people, they could be good for you, or they could be bad for you. I’m not advocating for them to be held to the same standards as a stranger in your life, but I am encouraging a tiny bit of accountability and critical thinking.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-situation-today-forever-a-nomad&quot;&gt;the situation today: forever a nomad?&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been back in Bangalore for two years now; a place I have previously lived in for around 12 years at a stretch, which is still my longest stretch yet. This time though, it’s been two years, and in several ways, it has been the best yet, and in other ways, it has been just the &lt;em&gt;cleansing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; my soul needed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first time (probably ever) I feel like I want to really stay in a place, and &lt;em&gt;I&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; get to make that decision, as opposed to a visa. For the time being, I don’t even crave travel that much, although I’m fairly sure that that will return.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;closing thoughts&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of, and also because of, all the twists and turns, I am genuinely glad about where I am right now. The future feels a bit easier to realistically think about. There is one, albeit massive in its own way, less uncertainty in my life and it feels good.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;currently listening to: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=JFXwocn8MrM&amp;amp;t=926s&quot;&gt;Love in the Void by Hammock&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>coming back to life</title>
        <published>2025-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              likith
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drlikith.com/blog/coming-back-to-life/"/>
        <id>https://drlikith.com/blog/coming-back-to-life/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://drlikith.com/blog/coming-back-to-life/">&lt;p&gt;If you had told me two years ago that, two years from then, I would be in Bangalore, doing primarily video-editing as a job, for my friend’s financial advisory company, I’d probably laugh it off as completely insane. I have found myself in similar situations over the past decade or so, where my life at one point in time, would probably have been unrecognisable to me 2-4 years prior. For a big chunk of my life, I was barely in touch with what I really wanted to do, but I’m happy to say that that has gradually been getting further and further away from the truth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;career&quot;&gt;career&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After spending five years learning the ins and outs of how atoms behave, what electrons do, and their implications thereof, I slowly came to a painful realisation towards the end: While I genuinely enjoyed certain aspects of it, I didn’t really want to keep doing research for the rest of my career. I knew this beyond a shadow of doubt during my postdoc position for which I did DFT (&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sci-hub.se&#x2F;10.1021&#x2F;jp960669l&quot;&gt;Density Functional Theory&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) for a primarily experimental research group. Of course this pursuit itself taught me a lot of lessons that have come to be invaluable to me, as a person, and this is true for the topic too.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I successfully pivoted towards data analytics and I did enjoy it a lot, and thought, for a second, that I had found my path. Working for Deloitte (for &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.mtb.com&#x2F;personal&quot;&gt;M&amp;amp;T Bank&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; as a client) was a lot of fun. It brought  the problem-solving aspect that I enjoyed during my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;scholar.google.com&#x2F;citations?user=jrlwT9IAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;research&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and combined that with a fast-paced, high-stakes environment with a supportive manager, and in this environment, I daresay I thrived.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All seemed well, until I decided to come back to Bangalore, and continue along the same career path. Things didn’t work out as I expected, and the next thing I knew, I had been job hunting for about a year and a half. I had been learning video editing (using only &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ffmpeg.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ffmpeg&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; at the time, mind you) as a hobby. Cut to a couple of months later, and I was now primarily a video editor at &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.instagram.com&#x2F;getwizr&#x2F;?hl=en&quot;&gt;Wizr Wealth&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a company that I am proud to say my friend had started a few years ago. Some of the perks include:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get to use whatever software I want for the work that I do. I get to use python, emacs, and linux itself, and it really does feel like home in a lot of ways (looking at you, &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;mse.ufl.edu&#x2F;people&#x2F;name&#x2F;nancy-ruzycki&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Dr. R&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get to use my camera on a regular basis, and I have gotten to learn lots of things about studios, lighting, etc.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am not bound by rigid hierarchies and meaningless (to me) rules which is typical, but of course, not always true, in larger organisations (in my experience at least)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get to code, but I don’t really &lt;em&gt;have&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;climbing-journey&quot;&gt;climbing journey&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first tried rock climbing in Seattle. It brought me uncomfortably and scarily close to my fear of heights&#x2F;falling. But I started to notice something when I started trying it more. I had managed to go around 5 years being in Golden, Colorado, being so sure of my fear, that I always refused to try it even though it was practically everywhere. I noticed myself mentally so engaged with the activity, that I wasn’t able to think of anything else. It wasn’t too many things to hold at once in my mental bandwidth&#x2F;scope of attention, but, a little bit more importantly, not too few either. Which was what has made continuing to go to the gym much harder for me. Not only was it the right level of mentally engaging, I also noticed my sleep improving, my general energy levels, mental state, and just generally how I felt about myself all saw improvements. Gainesville had a smaller-sized, more cave-inspired routes matching the climbing territory of the gym. I even used to take my climbing shoes when I travelled for work, and tried to go there before having to head back. This has been a lot of fun too. Currently, I’ve been going to one in Bangalore for probably around a year-and-a-half now, and I have liked it a lot, although there definitely have been some off-seasons, I am genuinely surprised that I have persisted this long with something even after ’setbacks’. I just sent my second Level-4, which, I guess is equivalent to V3-V4 at least. It wasn’t easy at all. It hasn’t been easy, or at least, I remember it being easier to do some moves that take more strength for me now, but the progress I have been noticing in myself has been consistent. I decided to invest in myself and bought the 6-month membership, which is about to enter the last month in a few days. It has been very rewarding to go, and as a bonus, the more I go, the lesser each session costs. I participated in a boulder social event where I had a lot of fun, and did pretty well in identifying the levels I was relatively comfortable with and made the most of the time. I did try some harder ones, most of them turned out to be level-4s, one of which I projected the entire day today and finally sent (completed) it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Book Review: Clockwork Angel</title>
        <published>2024-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2024-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              likith
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drlikith.com/blog/book-review-clockwork-angel/"/>
        <id>https://drlikith.com/blog/book-review-clockwork-angel/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://drlikith.com/blog/book-review-clockwork-angel/">&lt;p&gt;First things first: I am painfully aware of how long it has been since my last post. Lots of things have happened, to say the very least, but I’d rather dip my toes back in the pool with a post that is slightly less overwhelming than a life updates post. That said, here are a few micro-updates anyway, because, well, it’s been a long, long time since I have posted here. I’ve been in Bangalore for about a year now. After a metric tonne of education, and a pivoted beginning of a career, employment still eludes me. Equally, if not more, important though, is the fact that I finally met the love of my life. Excited to read that ’life updates’ post yet?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, without further ado, let’s get to the book. It has been around a year since I read a book with fantasy elements, which was &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.goodreads.com&#x2F;book&#x2F;show&#x2F;35068705-the-poppy-war&quot;&gt;Poppy War&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by R.F. Kuang. Over the past year or so, I have begun to read and enjoy romance, as a genre. Some of the books i have absolutely loved (in no particular order) are: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.goodreads.com&#x2F;book&#x2F;show&#x2F;43884209-get-a-life-chloe-brown&quot;&gt;Get a Life, Chloe Brown&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.goodreads.com&#x2F;book&#x2F;show&#x2F;49976087-take-a-hint-dani-brown&quot;&gt;Take a Hint, Dani Brown&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by Talia Hibbert; and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.goodreads.com&#x2F;book&#x2F;show&#x2F;55648820-seven-days-in-june&quot;&gt;Seven Days in June&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; by Tia Williams. For someone who has been out of touch with their emotions for a majority of their lives, and is more accustomed to reading fantasy and thrillers&#x2F;spy novels, this has been a refreshing change of pace. The way emotions like love, infatuation, fear, heartbreak, grief are described, and also the ways in which they manifest in our bodies and on our faces, have left me spellbound at how much I seem to be delighted by them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwork Angel has brought me back to the fantasy genre, with a romance arc (or two? I’m not entirely sure) in the backdrop of it all, and I am absolutely here for it. While I do wish I’d found it much, much earlier, I am very glad I was recommended it by someone very special to me. Firstly, I am used to books taking their time to really get into the action, but here, we are dropped almost instantly into the thick of it. I hadn’t even realised you could do such a thing; I am hooked. Of course, through this, as well as the rest of the story, as with any first book of a fantasy series, there is a good bit of world-building, which is very tastefully done. I never felt like I was taken away from the characters or the story-line to be told about the world and how things work (or don’t work, as the case may be). The world-building was woven in expertly into the storytelling in a way that felt very seamless and interesting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as characters go, Will and Jem have to be two of the most intriguing characters I have come across in a while. While Will has this irreverent, uncontainable rage and an energy that just refuses to be told what to do, Jem is a very calming, comforting presence seemingly with all the patience in the universe, and they complement each other so well. If I am walking into a fight with mythical Downworlders, this is the duo I would wish for; for motivating me when I need it, as well as to fight alongside me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book also touches upon the concept of found family in a way that tugs at my traumatised heartstrings like few other books have. Here are some quotes I highlighted, that I related to so hard, I cried.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not sure there is anyone in the Institute who is not an orphan&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, we are not here just because we have nowhere else, we need nowhere else, because we have the Institute, and those who are in it are our family.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… and one can build one’s own family.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that a group that has found each other, and put in the work day after day, year after year, and is as tight-knit as any group, bound by blood or not, could possibly be, is so heartwarming.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am very, very excited to read the next book in this series, and get to know these characters even better. I know I haven’t discussed other characters, and a lot about the story itself, but this is my first post in long time, and I want to manage my (and your) expectations and not overwhelm myself out of this. Here’s hoping I post more often here.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Consistency vs. Persistence</title>
        <published>2023-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              likith
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drlikith.com/blog/consistency-vs-persistence/"/>
        <id>https://drlikith.com/blog/consistency-vs-persistence/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://drlikith.com/blog/consistency-vs-persistence/">&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of people out there, I have had a long rollercoaster of a relationship with consistency. Not only would I set these ridiculously high standards for myself, I would pile on that with the expectation of consistency. It left me crushed and feeling miserable about myself for a long time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day, as a thought experiment, I let go of consistency as a bare minimum level of acceptance for myself, just to see what effect it would have on me, how I felt, and what happened to the relationship between me and the thing. Here’s an oversimplified example: Journaling has been a habit close to my heart for most of my life. I have journaled in one form or another for over 2 decades now, but I’ve rarely been ’consistent’. My go-to response to whenever I fell off the so-called wagon was to be disappointed in myself. &lt;em&gt;How could I do this AGAIN!?!&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; Over time, I’d develop this mental barrier against journaling, and it would feel like this ridiculously annoying chore that I’d always end up feeling ’too tired’ for. (by the way, the recent learning that while physical tiredness is definitely a thing, but tiredness is also sometimes an emotional response!! this blew my mind!) What started with that tiny thought experiment was a radical overhaul of my internal narrative. Letting go of the expectation of consistency meant that I was actually more likely to get back into it after a ’dry spell’, with just as much enthusiasm as the last time and not having to deal with all the drama that came with it. Overall, that sounds like a net positive effect to me, and that is without even accounting for the fact that I don’t feel as bad about myself on a regular basis.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Persistence is well aware of the fact that there will of course be periods in my life where I won’t be able to prioritize all the things that bring me joy and health, but is also self-assured that I trust myself to periodically check in with myself and, most importantly: listen. This story has played out in similar ways for me with a lot of my creative pursuits, including writing itself. I’ve gotten better at bringing things back, or getting back into things after a while and not associating it with a sense of self-shame. It still stings. My perfectionist tendencies aren’t dormant or anything; I’ve just gotten better at not taking them as seriously &lt;em&gt;all. the. time.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; I used to think if I let go of these standards, it would be a slippery slope to the absolute oblivion of never doing anything. That though, is just another example of a voice that needn’t be given that much attention. I have, in fact, found that when my basic needs are being met, I generally do enjoy and improve and follow all these callings, just at a different pace than I would have expected.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;northwood_concert.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;photography&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;photography has been another one of those things. Northwood was great to watch and I&#x27;m grateful I got to take some pictures&lt;&#x2F;figcaption&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here’s a takeaway: Show up, even if shabbily&#x2F;imperfectly; don’t let perfectionism paralyze you. Set your future self up for success, don’t make them feel bad about themselves, be nice to them, and they will have a better shot at doing fun and fulfilling things.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S.: this website was created on International Women’s Day 2022. It’s been a little over a year now, and I’ve enjoyed this a lot. I hope this can reach more eyes in the future, so, if you know anyone who might enjoy any of this, please share it with them :)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
